INSTRUCTOR: Welcome back.
I am so excited to have you
learn this week about date,
time, and text functions.
These are really
invaluable skills to know.
They're fairly foundational and
easy to wrap your head around,
but what it allows
you to do is really
get in and start
cleaning your data
and formatting your data in
a way that is going to be,
ultimately, really
helpful for you.
These are skills that
I use fairly regularly,
especially when we get into
the text portion of the videos
this week.
Today, we're going to focus
primarily on that date and time.
And these are a
series of functions
that really get at extracting
information in the format
that we want.
We can also start to do
some math using dates.
So if I want to know how many
days ago something happened,
or how many hours that you
worked so I know what to pay you
out, if I'm working
in payroll, these
become really critical to
how businesses function.
And so what we'll be doing
is using our ad events data.
You're welcome to
use your ad events
data that you have been using.
We're going to be just working
on a small subset of this data,
because I really want to
show you how this works.
You can download this,
essentially, the same one.
It's going to look
a smidge different,
but, overall, it's going
to be very similar.
This has all of the different
date and time informations
that we're going to
extract or calculate today.
And then we're also
going to be working
on another video on
our text information.
So feel free if you want to
download just this version
with our seven events that
we're going to be looking at,
you're more than welcome to.
You're also welcome to
continue to use this data.
So let's look at our
add events table.
We've been working in this
table a lot the last two weeks.
And it's extracted
a lot of data for us
already and done
that calculation.
So what time of day is it?
What is our event type?
Day of the week, and
gives us a timestamp.
We then went in and calculated
if it was a week day or weekend,
but when we're collecting
data, we usually
aren't getting data like that,
unless we're a data engineer
and we're actively
building that out and then
putting it in the database
because, maybe, that
is really important to
our daily functions.
And so a data engineer may be
going in and building those out
and so they exist
for everyone else.
But this is usually
what the data is going
to look like when we get it.
It's going to have our event ID.
And this is going to usually
be automatically assigned.
So every time there's a
new event that happens,
we're giving it a
unique identifier.
If you're in 2100 right now,
this is the primary key.
If you're not in 2100,
just forget I said that.
Then we have what
ad it was tied to,
because if we're
getting a bunch of data
and we're maybe running
multiple ad campaigns,
especially if we're
doing A/B testing,
we want to know exactly what
ad these impressions and likes
and shares happened on.
That way, we can
start to understand
how our ads
specifically performed,
rather than just on the whole.
Because if we just want
to know on the whole,
we can always
aggregate it, throw it
in a pivot table to
understand overall
what our annual
likes and shares are.
But if we're just
collecting on that level,
then we're not able to
go in and dig deeper.
So we want to
collect what exactly
ad we ran that garnered
those different events.
Then we have who did those
events so that way we
can understand, maybe, we have
some really high engaging users.
Maybe we have some that
are just brand new.
And they first started
clicking on our ads.
And then, ultimately, too, that
we can potentially connect it
into our e-commerce site.
If I'm running an ad
for a sale on shoes,
then I can try to connect my
user ID from my social media
into my e-commerce site.
So how did that ad actually
directly generate revenue?
And we can only do that
if we have that user ID
foreign key in this
data, rather than just
measuring share impressions.
And then we'll have timestamps.
And you'll notice when I copied
this over, instead of copying it
over as a really nice
timestamp, it copied over
as a bunch of numbers,
and that's perfectly fine.
This is just Excel's way
of storing that date time
information.
This is our date.
This is our time.
And we can change that back,
which we'll do in a second.
And then finally, we have
our different event types.
So down here, I have
formulas set up.
So as we build out
formulas, you'll
be able to see exactly what I
typed and it'll stay that way.
So first of all, we want
to convert this back
into a regular date time.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to copy this information,
and I'm just going
to paste it back.
Now, I'm going to come up to
my lovely data type formatting,
and I'm going to come down
to more number formats.
And when I hit more
number formats,
I'm going to be given a
lot of different options.
And in this case, I'm
going to click into date
and you'll see really quickly,
I have a lot of options here.
So I would like to, if
I just want to see date,
I can just click date.
And this is the format
I want to see it in.
That's great.
I can also start
switching things
around, make sure I have a
leading 0 if I need it right.
This is going to
be informed usually
by how the analyst
likes to see the data,
or, alternatively, how the
business tends to report it out
consistently.
So that's just a judgment
call that you'll make when
you're reporting things out.
So now what we do is
I'm going to come in
and I'm going to do a date
month, day year, with the time,
with an AM or PM stamp.
Perfect.
So now I have my date time in
a more user friendly format.
So that's something we look
at and we can instantly
see and understand.
So now let's look at hour.
So I'm going to start by
typing in hour because I
need to recalculate the time
of day that these happened.
Because then I can
start to recreate
a lot of those other tables,
the pivot table we created
last week, the
COUNTIFS from the week
before, and that's all
dependent on the hour
that these events occurred.
So Excel has a function
for, basically,
any extracting any
part of our datetime.
And datetime is the date
and time almost together.
We could either
extract the month,
which is going to be
like July and June.
It looks like from these
examples, the day of the month,
the year it happened, and the
hour, the minute, and second.
So let's just use
hour right now so
that way we can calculate
that time of day.
So we're going to do hour.
And super simply, we're just
going to click on our datetime
that we're interested in.
And you'll see that
it came as zero.
And you'll notice down here
what this first row of formulas
is going to be.
They didn't have a
formula, our does.
And at first, you
might be like, oh, no.
I did something wrong
because I returned to zero.
But look at the
date time over here,
Excel starts off
the hours at zero.
So 12 in the morning, so right
after midnight between 12:00
and 1:00 AM is going
to be an hour of zero.
Then the hour leading up to
11:00 PM to midnight is going
to be 23.
So let's go ahead and
fill this formula down.
But before I do that,
I want you to think,
do I need to put my
dollar signs in or not?
Do I need to lock
my formula in place?
In this case, I do not,
because I want to keep,
as I move my
formula down, I want
to keep referencing a new row.
And so that is what
I'm going to do.
So now I have zero, 8:00 AM,
19 because that's 7:00 PM, two,
which is PM, which is 14.
So when you're doing these
kinds of things, make sure
you're going back
and gut checking
to make sure that what you're
actually extracting makes sense,
and in this case, it does so.
So now that we have
hour calculated,
which you'll see down
here what this first row
formula looks like,
now let's go ahead
and calculate the time of day.
And so this is going to be our
morning, our evening, afternoon,
and night.
And that's not in the right
order, but we'll get there.
So first thing
that we need to do
is specify what we want
each one of these to be.
So morning, afternoon,
evening, and night.
Now, I need to
say start and end.
So what I need to
do now is I need
to go through and make
a judgment call on what
I want to be considered morning,
what I want to be considered
afternoon, evening, and night.
You can go ahead and
pick out your own numbers
if you don't agree with mine.
That's fine.
That's a different
judgment call,
and that's perfectly acceptable.
Usually, if we are really
interested in specific time
of days, then that's something
our business will set.
And at this point, that
business gets to be you.
So you get to set that
for your own document.
So in my case, I'm going to
start my morning probably around
6:00 AM because I know people
are starting to wake up.
Maybe the first thing they're
doing is checking social media,
and I want to capture what
that morning hours are,
and that first taste of
social media in the day.
And I'm going to end
this at 10:00 AM.
Then I'm going to say the
afternoon is my next option
that I can give, because this
is what was present in our data
originally.
I might actually say, I'm
going to end that at 11:00,
so it goes all the
way to 11:59 AM.
Then I'm going to start my
afternoon at 12:00 and continue
that until maybe 4:00 PM.
And then my evening hours will
start at 5:00, and, probably,
go to 8:00 or 9:00, maybe
depending on what my ads are.
Maybe I'm targeting families
with young children,
and so I know they're
in bed, hopefully,
for their sake by 9:00.
And so then I might
start pushing my ads
a lot more frequently
after that,
because I want to
maximize engagement
that's going to drive the
algorithms a little bit more.
So if I know when my
target audience is
interested and
interacting with my ads,
then I can pay a
little bit more money
to have my ads a little bit
more visible during those times.
Because, especially,
if I go back and link
to what ads are selling through
to my site and generating
revenue on my e-commerce
site, then I want to make sure
I'm maximizing my ad spend
for that specific time.
And the night will go from
10:00, but we can't just go--
this is 9:00 PM, which we'll
need to do some math again
in a second.
We're going to go from 10:00
PM all the way to 5:00 AM.
But like we noticed up here,
we actually use military time.
And so what I'm going to
do instead is saying, OK,
I have 12:00, that
stays the same.
And then I'm going to come up
here and look at-- let's see,
I've got 3:00, which is
15, so 4:00 turns into 16.
This turns into 17,
9:00 PM turns into 21,
which means this is 22.
And that stays at 5:00 because
we're rotating around 5:000 AM.
So now we can
calculate, based off
of the numbers we've
set our time of day
using those nested if
statements that you've
learned a couple of weeks ago.
So take a moment and see
if you can calculate,
if it's just do
morning and afternoon.
And then I'm going to
show you a different way
that we can construct
if statements that
is a little more intuitive,
that is a little more
advanced than the MyEducator
textbook goes, but makes
a lot more sense than 18
different nested if statements.
So the function I
really like to do,
if I'm dealing with more
than three conditions,
and in this case, I've
got four conditions,
is I like to rely on ifs.
And what ifs does
is it says, OK,
here is a condition
I'm going to check.
If this one's not
true, then I'm going
to move on to this next
condition and the next condition
and the next condition,
instead of you having
to go if, fill in the
blank, if that's false,
another if statement.
This does it and builds
it in and it just
makes it a little bit
more cleaner to deal with.
So first things first, let's go
ahead and look at our morning.
So if our hour is less
than or equal to six then--
but if we are just start
going through it like this,
we're not going to be able
to account for our five
being different.
So we actually need to use
our end because we have
a start point and an endpoint.
And, unfortunately, Excel
doesn't have a very nice
between function, and
so we have to construct
this in a specific way.
So if our hour is less than
or equal to our end time
and greater than or
equal to our start time,
let's make sure we've
got our hour in there,
then I'm going to
call it morning.
Now, I could type that all
up again for afternoon,
but I can also
just copy and paste
because we're, basically,
saying the same thing.
I just need to adjust what
cells I'm referencing.
So I changed these
from 12 to 13,
keeping my hour
reference intact.
Now I'm going to do the
same exact thing again,
and I'm going to move
from 13 down to 14.
Perfect.
Now with the night, I'm not
going to be approaching it
the same way, because if
something is happening at 11:30
PM, that's going
to be in our 22.
And then if, which is bigger
than 22 and bigger than 5,
but if something is
happening at 4:00 AM,
time is cyclical where
numbers are linear.
So I can't have
something, like 4:00 AM,
which is earlier than 5:00
and later than 11:00 PM.
And that makes sense the
way we think about time,
but it doesn't work when
we're converting things
to numbers like this.
So the other thing we need
to consider is our end.
And in this case,
something can not
be simultaneously bigger
than 22 and less than 5.
So in this case, we need
to use an or statement.
So if my hour is greater
than or equal to 22,
or my hour is less
than or equal to 5,
then I'm going to output night.
And then I'm going to hit Enter.
So now, I'm going
to drag that down.
But what happened when
I just drag that down?
I didn't lock my formula in.
And so when I click on it to get
checked, because I'm like, whoa,
these all shouldn't be zero.
That makes no sense.
That means there's
something going
on with my formula that's not
doing what I expect it to do.
And so you'll see when
I autofilled it down,
the first row, it brought
my references down a row.
Same thing with this second one.
And my very end isn't even on
my reference table anymore.
So take a second.
Pause the video
and try to fix it.
So I'm going to come
up to I3, and I am just
going to start to
add my dollar signs.
First, I need to evaluate
if I need any dollar
signs in front of my H3.
In this case, when
I come down, I
don't want to keep referencing
the hour on the first entry.
I want it to keep moving down
as I move my formula down,
so I don't need
dollar sign there.
I do need dollar sign because
I wanted to lock in morning,
and so I need to
come up and I just
need to start adding
my dollar signs.
And really, I just
need the dollar sign,
in this case, in front of
the number, because I'm not
moving my formula
across columns,
I'm moving it down rows.
So I only need the
dollar sign to show up
in front of the thing I don't
want to move down as I move--
my formula moves down.
If you wanted to, you could
completely add dollar signs
in front of the D as well.
And that's going to make sure
that you are for sure being safe
that B to D rows, 12 through
15, are not going anywhere.
And, again, I need
to be careful here.
And then let's
see if that works.
I'm going to click
and drag down.
So I thought I locked
everything into place,
but it looks like I missed one.
And so, again, that's why it's
really important to come down
a couple rows when
you're working
in these really
complex series in order
to make sure that everything's
sticking where we expect it to.
So now I need to come in and
lock in my B12, B13, B14,
and B15.
Now let's move that down.
Perfect.
And that is everything
I would expect it to be.
So I'm checking
8:00 AM is morning.
Yep.
That looks right.
19 is evening.
Also looks great.
Perfect.
So now I get to just use day of
the month, which is a completely
different function.
So in this case, I'm
going to go with month
and then put in my date
time and hit Enter.
And so now I know which
month things are happening.
And so if I wanted to
build out a pivot table
to understand my
trends over time,
now I can do that really
easy because I don't really
care so much about the
day in this specific case.
I care more about where
it falls in the month.
And maybe where it falls in the
year as far as my month goes.
So now I can do the same
thing with day of week.
So when I do week, I have
two different options.
I have weekday or weeknum.
In this case, I want to know
what day of the week it is.
I want to know if this is a
Monday, a Tuesday, a Saturday,
and it's going to
return a number, which
works for me because that
number is going to be
consistent across everything.
So we select my
datetime, weeknum.
That gives me my week in
the year, I need weekday.
Oh, my goodness, weekday.
Perfect.
And if I wanted to, I
could use an if statement
to convert these.
But I think that works
just fine for me.
So now what I'm going to do is
I'm going to look up a calendar,
and I'm going to
go back to July.
And July 26 was a Saturday.
So in this case, I start
counting one on Sunday.
So I've got one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven.
Perfect.
And then I need to know
that if it's a weekday.
So let's do another
if statement.
I'm just going to use
one if, in this case,
because I either need to know
if it's a weekend or a week day.
So that's only one if statement.
So if, or do or.
So if this number equals
seven, which we just determined
was a Saturday, or this number
equals one, which we just
determined was a Sunday.
Then say, and I
use my quotes here
because this isn't a
true or false where
I don't need quotes or a number,
I'm trying to return some text.
So if it's either
one, which is Sunday,
or seven, which is
Saturday, call it a weekend.
If it's not one of those,
then it's just a weekday.
And then I drag that down.
Now we can do some math.
So how long ago from today
did this event occur?
What we need to do is
come in and say equals.
And we got to figure out,
first of all, what our--
oops.
Oops.
My goodness.
OK.
I get it.
So I need to come down here
and fix this really quick.
OK day of month, day
of week, weekend.
Perfect, and then how long
ago, needs to be right here.
So-- and then let's wrap that.
So how long ago.
We need to figure
out what today is.
And I could come in and I
could say, OK it is 9, 10,
2025 at 11:03 AM.
I could do that.
Then I would have to
come in every single day,
or every time I want to write my
report and update that manually.
And that's not going to be
a good time for anybody.
We're going to be likely to
make mistakes because then we're
entering in things manually.
And so step one of
this, to determine
how long ago an event occurred,
is to use the Today function.
And the Today function,
we still use parentheses,
but we don't put
any parentheses in.
So now you can
see what today is.
Then I could also see, if I
wanted to, what the time is.
And that gives me
the date and time.
So depending on how granular you
want to work, you can choose.
In this case where we
do have date and time,
I'm going to use now.
And then I need to know
what the difference is
between now and then.
So what I need to do then is
subtract my original date time.
And this isn't a
super useful number.
This doesn't make any sense.
So I need to come
up to my custom
and change that to a number.
So now I know this
is about 46 days ago.
The older we get, the
bigger that number
gets, because it was happened
a lot further back in time.
So now I have that 46,
that's the date part.
So that's how many days ago.
And then the 45 is what is
the time difference included
in that.
If I wanted to just
use today, then I
can also do that and,
again, switch it to number.
And it's always going to be
0.99 because I don't have
the time included in there.
And that is how we
are going to be using
some of those date and time.
There are other
functions and formulas,
which the textbook
will walk you through.
This is just that high level.
Let's blend what we've learned
in the past with our if
statements.
How do we think about
this in context?
What do businesses do with this?
And then how can we apply
our different formulas
to understand our data better?
Thanks, and we'll see you
as we talk about time.